Finding Aid for Nicholas H. Steneck papers, 1971-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nicholas H. Steneck papers 1971-2005
Steneck, Nicholas H.
2008141 Aa 2
Papers of Nicholas Steneck, University of Michigan history professor. Contains materials on programs, projects, committees, and task forces Steneck was involved in as well as course materials. The collection reveals interests in the history of science, ethics and values in science, research integrity, and the history of the University of Michigan.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received from Nicholas H. Steneck (Donor No. 9775 ) in 2006.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Nicholas H. Steneck joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1970. Originally from the East Coast, he earned his B.S. at Rutgers University in 1962. He then attended the University of Wisconsin for graduate school. There he received an M.A. in history and a Ph.D. in medieval history and the history of science in 1970. Steneck's wife, Margaret Steneck, also received her M.A. and Ph.D. in Tudor-Stuart history from the University of Wisconsin. She worked as a Lecturer in history at the University of Michigan, and the two team-taught History 265, a course they developed on the history of the University Michigan.
As an historian of science, Steneck displayed both a strong humanities-based perspective and a strong interest in science and related ethical issues. In 1983 he proposed a Science-Humanities Center, to be housed in the historic Detroit Observatory, that would "coordinate activities that fall between the sciences and the humanities" (letter to Steiner, 1983). The melding of these two interests and perspectives helps explain many of the programs and projects Steneck worked on during his career. After serving as an active member and as an Associate Director, Steneck was named Director of the Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (CIVS) in 1982, a post he held until 1990, when he ended his directorship to focus on the University of Michigan Historical Center for the Health Sciences (HCHS). In 1990, Steneck created and became Director of HCHS, through which he hoped to preserve the history of the important role of the University's health sciences programs in promoting human health. He held this post until 1996 when Howard Markel took over as Director. (Markel later recast HCHS as the Center for the History of Medicine.) Steneck served for many years as LS&A Co-Director of the Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (Inteflex), which sought to provide a more solid humanities component to premedical education while transitioning Inteflex students more quickly from undergraduate into medical school. He also served during the mid-1980s on the LSA/Medical School Task Force and the LSA/Medical School Liaison Committee, helping to evaluate and adjust the Inteflex program. Beginning in 1987, he worked to organize a Michigan chapter and Michigan conferences for Science Technology and Society (STS).
As his involvement in programs like CIVS and STS indicate, Steneck had an interest in ethics and values in scientific research. This is also evident in some of the committees and task forces he either served on or chaired, including the Integrity of Scholarship Task Force (ISTF) from 1982-1984, The Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility (AFAR) Committee from 1984-1986, the Committee on the Use and Care of Animals in 1987, the Conference on Teaching Ethics and Values (CTEV) Committee from 1987-1989, the Public Health Service Advisory Committee on Research Integrity from 1991-1993, and the Panel of Inquiry into Federally-sponsored Human Radiation Research at the U of M in the Post-WWII Era from 1994-1995.
Steneck joined the College of Engineering faculty in 1996 as Adjunct Professor of Ethics in Industrial and Operations Engineering with primary responsibility for implementing the ethics thread of Curriculum 2000. After retirement, Steneck continued as Emeritus Professor of History in LS&A and remained active on the topic of integrity in scientific research as a consultant to the U.S. Office of Research Integrity (ORI) and in other forums.
Steneck's publications include Science and Creation in the Middle Ages (1976), The Microwave Debate (1984), the ORI Introduction to the Responsible Conduct of Research (2004), and articles on the history of research misconduct policy, animal use in research, classified research and academic freedom, faculty governance, and the role of values in university research.
The Nicholas H. Steneck Papers contain materials on programs, projects, committees, and task forces Steneck was involved in as well as course materials. The collection reveals interests in the history of science, ethics and values in science, research integrity, and the history of the University of Michigan. The papers are arranged in four series: Programs and Projects, Committees and Task Forces, Teaching Materials and Slides.
Subjects:
University of Michiana--Faculty.; University of Michiana--History.; University of Michigan. Collegiate Institute for Values and Science.; University of Michigan. Historical Center for the Health Sciences.; University of Michigan. Integrated Premedical-Medical Program.; University of Michigan.; Values--Study and teaching.; Science--Social aspects.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Programs and Projects
  The Programs and Projects (1 linear foot, 1976-1998) series contains correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes, program and funding proposals, handwritten notes, background and other working materials, and reports related to programs and projects Nick Steneck started or was closely involved with during his career. The first of these is the Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (CIVS). CIVS began as an evening seminar series in 1976 and was expanded into a Collegiate Institute in Winter 1977 as a forum for exploring practical and philosophical questions related to scientific research and human values. Steneck's papers contain a CIVS annual report that Steneck authored, correspondence, notes and papers on CIVS programs, documents related to the initial search for CIVS Fellows, and other documents from the beginning of CIVS. Papers on the Historical Center for the Health Sciences (HCHS) contain correspondence, meeting minutes, a prospectus and a 6 month progress report, both authored by Steneck, and folders relating to projects either undertaken by HCHS or projects that pre-dated HCHS but were directly related to HCHS interests. These include the Historic Instruments and Observatory Preservation (HIOP) Committee, surveys of historic art related to the hospital and medical school, Old Main Hospital preservation, Detroit Observatory preservation, the Kellogg Project on the history of African American health care, and a CD-ROM on the history of instruments of gastrointestinal endoscopy. Steneck was also involved with the Integrated Premedical-Medical Program, or Inteflex, both on committees and as LS&A Co-Director. His papers related to this program include reports, correspondence, budget information, and curriculum discussions. They also contain agendas, minutes, and correspondence on the related LSA/Medical School Liaison Committee and the LSA/Medical School Task Force. In the mid to late-1980s, Steneck made an effort to begin a Michigan chapter of Science Technology and Society (STS), and his papers contain correspondence, notes, questionnaires, conference participant lists, and meeting minutes on this topic.
  - Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (CIVS)
    - 1984/85 Program, 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1983/84 Program, 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1982/83 Program, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Business 1976-1982 (Box 1)
    - CIVS 3rd Conference 1982 (Box 1)
    - Corporate Affiliates Program 1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Subcommittee 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - EHVIST and Funding 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Fellows 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - First Annual Report, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Future 1982-1987 (Box 1)
    - Future of CIVS Proposal 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Funding 1979-1985 (Box 1)
    - Pending 1984 (Box 1)
    - Presidential Initiatives Fund 1987 (Box 1)
    - Proposal Letters 1984-1987 (Box 1)
    - Recombinant DNA Collection--Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Recombinant DNA Collection List 1983 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduates Initiative Fund 1987 (Box 1)
  - ENIAC
    - Move and Display 1986-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Faculty Governance at the University of Michigan: Principles, History, and Practice: A Report for the University Community, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Historical Center for the Health Sciences (HCHS), University of Michigan
    - Accounts--General 1990-1997 (Box 1)
    - AGA/ASGE CD-ROM--Gastroenterology 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Alumni/Graduates--Correspondence 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - American Astronomical Society 1987 (Box 1)
    - Art Survey--Medical School Portraits 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    - Art Survey--Miscellaneous 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Observatory 1983-1988 (Box 1)
    - Guidelines for Developing MARC Archival and Manuscripts Control Format Records for Collections in the History of Health Care and the Health Sciences, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Historic Instrument and Observatory Preservation (HIOP) Committee Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence 1984-1987 (Box 1)
    - HIOP Correspondence 1984-1988 (Box 1)
    - HIOP Funding Letters 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Historic Instrument Survey, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Historical Collection Committee 1989 (Box 1)
    - Hospital Art Project 1990 (Box 1)
    - Hospital History Vol. 1-5, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Instrument Survey Responses 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Kellogg Project 1996-1998 (Box 1)
    - North Hall 1991 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes and Annual Report 1997 (Box 2)
    - Memos/Internal Correspondence 1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Materials 1989-1998 (Box 2)
    - Old Main 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Old Main Administrative Wing Preservation Proposal 1987-1989 (Box 2)
    - Photos for Publications, undated (Box 2)
      (Photographs related to HCHS projects and interests, including the historic instrument survey, the historic art and portraits surveys, the Detroit Observatory, and Old Main.)
    - Progress Report at 6 months 1990 (Box 2)
    - Prospectus and Letters 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Related Organizations 1986 (Box 2)
    - The Social and Cultural History of Medicine and Health: A Guide to Bibliographic Resources at the University of Michigan, 1991 (Box 2)
    - State Ties--Correspondence 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Vice Provost for Medical Affairs (VPMA) Interviews 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (Inteflex)
    - Admissions 1994 (Box 2)
    - Bioethics 1994 (Box 2)
    - Budget 93-94 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Budget 94-95 1994-1996 (Box 2)
    - CRLT Grant (Curr.) 1994 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum Initiative 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - IFX 100-103 1994 (Box 2)
    - Inteflex--Academic Performance 1995 (Box 2)
    - Inteflex LSA Review Committee--Report 1993 (Box 2)
    - Inteflex Review 1995-1997 (Box 2)
    - Intro to Health Care 1994 (Box 2)
    - LSA Curriculum Committee 1994 (Box 2)
    - New Curriculum 1994 (Box 2)
    - Office 1994-1998 (Box 2)
    - Sexuality 1994 (Box 2)
    - Science 1994 (Box 2)
    - Statistics 1994 (Box 2)
    - Steering Committee 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - LSA/Medical School Liaison Committee 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - LSA/Medical School Task Force--Agendas, Minutes, Memos 1982-1986 (Box 2)
  - LSA/Medical School Task Force--Report 1984 (Box 2)
  - Science, Technology, and Society (STS), Michigan
    - Background and Miscellaneous Material 1974-1988 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Organizational Questionnaires, Participant Lists 1987 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes 1987-1988 (Box 2)
- Committees and Task Forces
  The Committees and Task Forces (1.5 linear feet, 1987-1998) series consists of meeting agendas and minutes, correspondence, background and other working materials, and final reports relating to various committees and task forces Steneck either served on or chaired during his career. Perhaps the most significant records in this series are those relating to the Integrity of Scholarship Task Force (ISTF), which Steneck chaired. This was the first such task force and was met with much interest from both within and outside the University of Michigan. Two folders of material relating to requests from outside the university for copies of the ISTF Final report attest to this interest. The ISTF material also includes information on the nomination process for the task force, correspondence, handwritten notes, research into related policies, questionnaires, report drafts, and the final report. Steneck led the Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility (AFAR) Committee, which is represented in this series with memos and correspondence, letters seeking funding, and papers and a final report authored by Steneck. The series also includes materials on the Committee on the Use and Care of Animals, formed to address the 6-month probationary status given to the University of Michigan Animal Research Facility by the American Association for Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care; the Human Radiation Committee, or Panel of Inquiry into Federally-sponsored Human Radiation Research at the University of Michigan in the Post-World War II Era; the Conference on Teaching Ethics and Values (CTEV) Committee; History Department Curriculum Committee; the Research Policies Committee; the Humanities Advisory Committee; History of Medicine Professor Search; and Steneck's involvement in the inauguration ceremonies of university presidents James J. Duderstadt and Lee C. Bollinger.
  - Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility (AFAR) Committee
    - Background Info 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Final Report and Comments/Correspondence 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Foundations and Support Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Limiting Research--Report and Comments 1984 (Box 2)
    - Notes, minutes, drafts, correspondence 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Publicity 1983 (Box 2)
  - Committee on the Use and Care of Animals 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Committee for the Inauguration of James J. Duderstadt 1988 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Teaching Ethics and Values (CTEV) Committee
    - CTEV Conference 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - 5th Conference 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - History Department Curriculum Committee 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - History of Medicine Professor Search 1974-1979 (Box 2)
  - Human Radiation Committee 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Humanities Advisory Committee 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Integrity of Scholarship Task Force (ISTF)
    - Correspondence and Drafts 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Ethics--Replies to Questionnaires 1983 (Box 3)
    - Follow up Discussions 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Follow up Meetings 1984 (Box 3)
    - Input--Phone and Miscellaneous Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Integrity of Scholarship and Publication Requests 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Internal Questionnaire #2 1984 (Box 3)
    - Letters to Committee 1984 (Box 3)
    - Maintaining the Integrity of Scholarship Report, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Meeting #7 and Drafts 1984 (Box 3)
    - Notes on Meetings 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Organizations with Policies 1983 (Box 3)
    - Other Guidelines 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Material 1982-1984 (Box 3)
    - Questionnaire #3 1984 (Box 3)
    - Questionnaire #4 1984 (Box 3)
    - Review of Interim Policy of Integrity of Scholarship 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Marshal--Bollinger Inauguration 1997 (Box 3)
  - Research Policies Committee 1990-1992 (Box 3)
- Teaching Materials
  The Courses subseries of the Teaching Materials (1.5 linear feet, 1971-2004) series contains mainly course syllabi, lecture schedules, and reading lists for the history courses Steneck taught. Several courses--UC 211, UC 342, UC 265, and UC 615--addressed research ethics and science and values, which fits with Steneck's other professional interests and activities. The Courses sub-series also contains correspondence and course material for several overseas summer programs Steneck participated in.
  - Courses
    - Hist 101 1971-1977 (Box 3)
    - Hist 263, 283--Schedules and Exams (Science to Newton) 1975-1991 (Box 3)
    - Hist 265--Campus Practicum (self-guided Central Campus tour) 1995, 2000-2005 (Box 3)
    - Hist 265--IRB Forms 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Hist 265--Oral History Assignment
      - 1998 (Box 3)
      - 1999 (Box 3)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 3)
      - 2004, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Hist 285--Fall/Winter 92-93 (Science, Technology and Society) 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Hist 392, 397--Scientific Revolution 1974-1978 (Box 3)
    - Hist 396--Critics of Science 1980 (Box 3)
    - Hist 396--Family Life and Education 1973 (Box 3)
    - Hist 396--Health Sciences at Michigan and Science and Policy After the Bomb 1990 (Box 3)
    - Hist 396--Intellectual Warfare (Box 3)
    - Hist 396--Technology and Society 1984 (Box 3)
    - Hist 398--Mysticism 1975 (Box 3)
    - Hist 421--Medieval Culture and Learning 1971, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Hist 422--Medieval Culture and Learning 1971 (Box 3)
    - Hist 586--Scientific Revolution (Box 3)
    - Hist 593--Science to Newton 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Hist 618, 619--History of Science 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - Hist 704--European Studies 1982 (Box 3)
    - Honors 199 Colloquium 1977 (Box 3)
    - MARC 213--Family Life and Education in the Late Middle Ages and Early Renaissance 1974 (Box 3)
    - MARC 223--Medieval Near East and the Steppes of Central Asia, 454--Paris from Abelard to Villon 1974 (Box 3)
    - MARC 432--Medieval Universities 1976 (Box 3)
    - Paleography--Winter 74 1974-1977 (Box 3)
    - Peace Studies 1984 (Box 3)
    - UC 211--Mini-Course on Professions, Research, and Ethics
      - UC 211--Correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - UC 211--Ethics and Professions 1986 (Box 3)
    - UC 265--Science and Values
      - UC 265--Correspondence 1981-1982 (Box 3)
      - UC 265--Correspondence 1983-1987 (Box 3)
      - UC 265--Funding 1984-1986 (Box 3)
      - UC 265--Science and Values 1977 (Box 4)
      - UC 265--Science and Values, Fall 1978 (Box 4)
      - UC 265--Science and Values, Winter 1979-1980 (Box 4)
      - UC 265--Science and Values, Fall 1980 (Box 4)
      - UC 265--Science and Values, Winter 1982 (Box 4)
      - UC 265--Science and Values November 1982 (Box 4)
      - UC 265--Science and Values, Winter 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - UC 342--Ethics and Professions 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - UC 615--Science and Values Summer Institutes 1991-1997 (Box 4)
    - 996--Rackham Research Responsibility Program 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Passau Summer Program 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - REF@UM, Curriculum 2000--Engineering Ethics 1997-1999 (Box 4)
    - Sarah Lawrence Summer Program 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - History of the University of Michigan
    The History of the University of Michigan subseries contains a self-guided tour of Central Campus authored by Nick and Margaret Steneck, who developed and team-taught a course on the history of the University. The rest of this sub-series consists of student papers for major assignments in the course. These include an oral history assignment and a major research paper. For the oral history assignment, students interviewed alumni or employees of the University with knowledge of some aspect or period of the University's history. These folders contain papers written from these interviews as well as interview transcripts and, in some cases, audio tape recordings of the interviews. The course research papers are arranged by topics such as Buildings, Athletics, or Greek System. As undergraduate assignments, these are not necessarily authoritative sources, but in many cases they contain first-person accounts of student life as well as university history on focused topics, often informed by primary sources, which likely have not been written on elsewhere.
    - U-M History Research Papers
      - Buildings 1987-2003, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Athletics 1989-2003, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Clubs, Organizations, and Facilities 1989-2003 (Box 4)
      - Faculty/Staff 1987-1998 (Box 4)
      - Greek System 1987-2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Housing 1988-1995 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1987-1992 (Box 4)
      - Monuments (Box 4)
      - Race/Ethnic Diversity 1999 (Box 4)
      - Service 1990-2002 (Box 4)
      - Scholarships 1987-1999 (Box 4)
  - International Student Pugwash (ISP)
    The subseries on International Student Pugwash (ISP) contains material on the formation and activities of an Ann Arbor chapter of ISP, for which Steneck served as faculty advisor.
    - Administrative Material 1984 (Box 4)
    - Chapter Activities and Advertising 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Chapter Charter 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence--Arms Control Simulation 1985 (Box 4)
    - Grants 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Mailing Lists/Contacts 1983 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter and Publicity 1981-1983 (Box 4)
    - Nuclear Arms Control Simulation 1985 (Box 4)
    - Organizing and Leadership Workshop 1984 (Box 4)
    - Pugwash Blurb 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Records 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - SPUSA Conference 1983 (Box 4)
- Slides
  The Slides (2 linear feet) series consists of slides that Steneck compiled or created, primarily about the history of the University of Michigan and the city of Ann Arbor. The slides contain pictures used in his UM practicum course. Slides also include material from the medical facilities, the engineering department, and the Detroit Observatory. Titles listed are the labels written on each individual slide box, which then contain a number of slides organized by categories. There are 13 slide boxes total.
  - Slide Notes (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor, 1940-"At Home in Ann Arbor" (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor, University of Michigan, sports, Shapiro, Duderstadt, Taylor Bell Foundation (Box 5)
  - Buildings I (Box 5)
  - Buildings II: scenes and views, maps, monuments, Angell, photo hunt, display (Box 5)
  - Engineering: Faculty, buildings, students, Phoenix, instruments, ENIAC, astronauts (Box 5)
  - Historical/Medical instruments, anatomical remains, HCHS (Box 5)
  - History of UM, 1817- (Box 6)
  - History of UM 1909-1967 (Box 6)
  - History of UM, 1968- (Box 6)
  - Medical: building, classes, faculty, nursing, pharmacy, dentistry (Box 6)
  - Misc. Slides; unlabeled medical and other (Box 6)
  - Observatory: history, instruments, restoration; preservation; general; medical school: basic science, classrooms, 298th hospital unit (Box 6)
  - Practicum
Related Material
Additional materials on many of the projects and organizations represented in the Steneck papers can be found in other Bentley Library records. The library holds collections for the Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (CIVS), the Historical Center for the Health Sciences (HCHS, known subsequently as the Center for the History of Medicine), the Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (Inteflex), and the Detroit Observatory. The CIVS collection has folders related to the Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility (AFAR) committee. The CIVS collection and the School of Public Policy collection both have some material on the Ann Arbor chapter of International Student Pugwash (ISP).
Steneck deposited research materials for his 1984 book The Microwave Debate, at the Gerald R. Ford Library. This includes "published material related to the biological effects of microwave radiation and government documents, acquired under the Freedom of Information Act, related to the microwave bombardment of the U.S. Embassy in Moscow" (Ford Library finding aid).